Guide to the Edward Cyrus Cole Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Edward Cyrus Cole papers
1935-1978
MS 908
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
38.83
(52 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, articles, speeches, book reviews, and material on the Yale School of Drama, including Cole's course notes, production notes, reports, financial papers and slides of productions. The subject files are of particular interest for the material from the early days of television, ca. 1948. Cole's work as a theater consultant is shown in the blue prints and other material prepared for theaters in Dresden, Malmo, Philadelphia and Stanford.
Cole, Edward Cyrus
Conditions Governing Access
This bulk of the materials are open for research. A file of student grades in the 1980 accession is restricted until April 8, 2055, and Accession 1986-M-032 is closed until processed.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Edward C. Cole, 1970 and 1980, and transferred from the Yale Drama School, 1985; the Yale Drama Library, 1989; and the Yale Art and Architecture Library, 2006.
Biographical / Historical
Edward C. Cole (1904-): faculty member of the Yale University School of Drama, 1930-1966; production consultant for TV station WRGB, Schnectady, 1944; theater planning consultant from 1937.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, articles, speeches, book reviews, and material on the Yale School of Drama, including Cole's course notes, production notes, reports, financial papers and slides of productions. The subject files are of particular interest for the material from the early days of television, ca. 1948. Cole's work as a theater consultant is shown in the blue prints and other material prepared for theaters in Dresden, Malmo, Philadelphia and Stanford.
Television; Theater architecture; Theater; Educators; Cole, Edward Cyrus; American Educational Theatre Association; Yale School of Drama; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory, 1948 May 28 - 1979 May 15
  - Listing of the Television File
    - A's
      - Television, Acting (Box 1)
      - Television Advertisements (Box 1)
      - Affiliated Committee For Television (Box 1)
      - Television, American Society (Box 1)
      - Television, Associates Inc. (Box 1)
      - Television, Audio (Box 1)
      - Television, Audience Surveys (Box 1)
    - B's
      - Television, Bibliography (Box 1)
      - Television, Broadcasters Association (Box 1)
      - TBA, Education Committee (Box 1)
      - TBA, Program Committee (Box 1)
    - C's
      - Television, Cameras and Their Operation (Box 1)
      - Television, Careers (Box 1)
      - Television, Color Transmission (Box 1)
      - Television, CBS (Box 1)
      - Television, Commerciar Operations (Box 1)
      - Television, Control Equipment (Box 1)
      - Television, Correspondence, Miscellaneous (Box 1)
      - Television, Correspondence, Specific: GE, ATS, RCA, NBC, WRBG, RKO, [illegible] (Box 1)
      - Television, Criticism of (Box 1)
      - Television, Crosby, John (Box 1)
      - Television, Cultural (Box 1)
      - Television, Current Events (Box 1)
    - D's
      - Television, Door of New York; letters (Box 1)
    - E's
      - Television, Economics (Box 2)
      - Television, Education by (Box 2)
      - Television, Electronics (Box 2)
      - Television, Engineering (Box 2)
      - Television, Equipment (Box 2)
      - Television 113, Exams and quizzes (Box 2)
      - Television, Excerpts and quotations (Box 2)
    - F's
      - Television, Federal Communications Commission (Box 2)
      - Television, Films (Box 2)
    - H's
      - Television, History of (Box 3)
    - I's
      - Television, Installations (Box 3)
    - J's
      - Joint Committee on Educational Television (Box 3)
    - M's
      - Television, Merchandising (Box 3)
      - Telvision, Music (Box 3)
    - N's
      - Television, Networks (Box 3)
      - Television, National Citizens Committee for Educational Television (Box 3)
      - Television, Nomenclature (Box 3)
    - O's
      - Television, Opaque Projection Practices (Box 3)
      - Television, Organizations (Box 3)
    - P's
      - Television, Day (Box 3)
      - Television, Periodicals (Box 3)
      - Television, Personnel (Box 3)
      - Television, Producers and ProducingGroups (Box 3)
      - Television, Producer's Manual (Box 3)
      - Television, Press Clippings (Box 3)
      - Television, Productions (Box 3)
      - Television, Production Costs (Box 3)
      - Television, Production Code (Box 3)
      - Television, Production, Pictorial Composition Programs, Current Events (Box 3)
      - Television, Program Development (Box 3)
      - Television, Program Schedules (Box 3)
      - Television, Projection, Large Screen (Box 3)
    - R's
      - Television, Randall School Course Receivers, Lighting (Box 4)
      - Television, Rehearsals (Box 4)
      - Television, Remotes (Box 4)
      - Television, Ross Reports (Box 4)
    - S's
      - Television, Scenery (Box 4)
      - Television, Scheduling Programs (Box 4)
      - Television, Scripts; 'Farmer Takes a Wife' (Box 4)
      - Television, Seminar, Plans for (Box 4)
      - Television, Shayon, Robert Lewis (Box 4)
      - Television, Sociology of (Box 4)
      - Television, Studio (Box 4)
      - Television, Studio Organization and Procedure (Box 4)
      - Television, Subscription TV (Box 4)
      - Television, System and its Ramifications (Box 4)
    - T's
      - Television and Theatre (Box 4)
    - U's
      - Television, University of Illinois (Box 4)
      - Television, University of [illegible] (Box 4)
    - W's
      - Television, Writing (Box 5)
      - Television, Workshops (Box 5)
      - Television, WAVZ Course (Box 5)
      - Television, WTIC (Box 5)
    - Y's
      - Television, Yale Committee (Box 5)
- Additional material, Accession 1980-M-006
  - Correspondence, 1945-1977
    - General, 1945-1971, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1-29)
  - Subject File, 1935-1978
    - Boston Herald Traveler Repertory Theater, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Organizations
      - American Educational Theatre Association, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - American National Theatre and Academy, 1952-1953, 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 32-34)
      - Arts Council of New Haven, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - National Council of the Arts in Education, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Television Broadcasting Association, 1946-1950 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Television
      - Early teaching materials, 1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Educational TV, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Notes for lectures, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Proposal for workshop, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - "Yale Interprets the News", transcripts, 1944-1948 (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - "Yale Interprets the News", transcripts, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Theatre Planning
      - "The Architectural Forum", 1935 January (Box 1, Folder 44)
      - Consulting service proposal, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
      - Drama 109, course questionnaire, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 46)
      - Drama-109, space performance questionnaire, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 47)
      - Drama 109, office space questionnaire, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Lecture, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      - Nagy - Multi - Screen Projection system Report, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Theatre specs, 1927-1966 (Box 1, Folder 51-52)
      - Yale Drama Plant, course questionnaire, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - Yale Drama Plant, faculty responses, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 54)
      - Yale Drama Plant, floor plans, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
      - Yale Drama Plant, Lighting Department Report, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 56)
      - Yale Drama Plant, proposal, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 57)
      - Yale Drama Plant, report, 1968 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 58)
      - Yale Drama Plant, report, Drama 109, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 59)
      - Yale Drama Plant, student questionnaire, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Wellesley summer theatre, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Yale Drama School
      - Alumni Board, National Seminar, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      - Alumni Fund, 1954-1955, 1964, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 63-66)
      - Alumni Fund lists, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 67)
      - Alumni Fund phonathons, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      - Alumni occupations, 1952-1963 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - Alumni records, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - 40th Anniversary appreciation letters, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - 40th Anniversary, Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - 40th Anniversary, Howland Memorial, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - 40th Anniversary program, 1965 November 6 (Box 2, Folder 74)
      - 40th Anniversary speeches, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 75)
      - Course notes, Elementary Play Production, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      - Course notes, Scene Design, 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 77-78)
      - Course notes, Stagecraft, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
      - Course notes, Television 113, 1944-1959 (Box 2, Folder 80-88)
      - Course notes, Television 113a, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 89-94)
      - Course notes, Television Writing, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 95)
      - Course notes, Theatre Management, undated (Box 2, Folder 96)
      - Faculty meeting minutes, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 97)
      - Operations, 1926,1957,1962 (Box 2, Folder 98)
      - Operating accounts, 1944-1946 (Box 2, Folder 99)
      - Production, Purple Dust, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 100)
      - Production, John Brown's Body, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 101)
      - Production budgets and schedules, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 102)
      - Production budgets, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 103)
      - Production budgets, Workshop, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 104)
      - Production budgets, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 105)
      - Production budgets, Workshop, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 106)
      - Production budgets, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 107)
      - Production budgets, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 108)
      - Production budgets, Workshop, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 109)
      - Production budgets, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 110)
      - Production cost estimates, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 111)
      - Production estimates, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 112)
      - Production income, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 113)
      - Production, miscellaneous writings and notes, 1957-1958, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 114)
      - Production, organization, undated (Box 2, Folder 115)
      - Production prospectus, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 116)
      - Production work assignments, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 117)
      - Purchasing, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 118)
      - Reports to the Dean, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 119)
      - Special fund accounts, 1945-1951 (Box 2, Folder 120)
  - Writings
    - Address by ECC, 1945-1965 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Design theory, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - "A Positive Step Forward", undated (Box 2, Folder 123)
    - "State Machinery in the U.S.", 1948 (Box 2, Folder 124)
    - "Technical Problems of the Stage", 1950 (Box 2, Folder 125)
    - Future of the theatre, undated (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Theatre architecture, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 127)
    - Theatre architecture, articles by ECC and Harold Burris - Meyer, undated (Box 2, Folder 128)
    - "Theatre and Technical Revolution", 1958 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - "Theatre off-Manhattan", 1963 (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - "Two Theatres for American Colleges", 1944 (Box 2, Folder 131)
    - Book reviews of ECC books, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1945-1978 (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - Newsclippings, 1948-1953 (Box 2, Folder 134)
    - Script, section of unidentified work, undated (Box 2, Folder 135)
    - Drama 113 grades, 1944-1965 (Box 2, Folder 136)
      Conditions Governing Access
      This file contains student grades and is restricted until April 8, 2055.
  - Blueprints and Theatre Plans, undated
    - Camp Lee, undated (Box 3, Folder 136)
    - Dresden, undated (Box 3, Folder 137)
    - Malmo, undated (Box 3, Folder 138-139)
    - Philadelphia Opera House, undated (Box 3, Folder 140)
    - Leland Stanford Memorial Hall, undated (Box 3, Folder 141)
  - Photographic Slides
    - Yale Drama School Productions
      - "Arms and Man" (Box 4)
      - "Devil's Disciple" (Box 4)
      - "Doll's House" (Box 4)
      - "Going Mad Again" (Box 4)
      - "Good Lieutenant" (Box 4)
      - "Masquerade" (Box 4)
      - "Night Ghost of Lower Gunk" (Box 4)
      - "Othello" (Box 4)
      - "Peer Gynt" (Box 4)
      - "Simple Life" (Box 4)
      - "Voyage" (Box 4)
    - Instruction slides for television class (Box 4)
    - Unidentified set design (Box 4)
- Additional material, 1930s-1970s; Accession 1986-M-032
  Closed until processed.
  - Speeches, galleys, scripts, personal, photographs (Box 1)
    - Elizabeth Elson (Mrs. Meyer Cohen), New York, NY, 1973 Oct 26; 1 (Box 22)
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - Mary Ellen Nemeth (nee Bute) interviewed by Donald Robinson, NYC, 1973 Mar 5; 1 (Box 23)
    - Charles Allen interviewed by Donald Robinson, New York City, 1972 Dec 24; 1 (Box 24)
    - H.C. Potter, 1974 May 8; 1 (Box 25)
    - Louis Simon, New York City, 1973 May 2; 1 (Box 26)
    - Donald Oenslager, New York City, 1972 May 4; 1 (Box 27)
    - Ed Cole Speech, Tribute to Stanley McCandles, 3 3/4 ips, 1/2 T Mono, 2 sides (1 of 2), 1 (Box 28)
    - Ed Cole Speech, Tribute to Stanley McCandles, 3 3/4 ips, 1/2 T Mono, 2 sides (2 of 2), 1 (Box 29)
    - Alumni luncheon, Harold Igo and Peter Reynard (side A) and interview with Boyd Smith, Sarasota, part one (side B), 1972 April 22; 1 (Box 30)
      General
      Recording begins one third of the way through the tape.
    - Interview with Boyd Smith, Sarasota (part two), 1972 April 23; 2 (Box 31)
    - WBZ, "After the Storm," circa 7:30-8:00 a.m., 1978 February 9; 1 (Box 32)
    - Durham Jazz Quartet, Corell, Wing, Wheeler and Katz, 1978 March 4; 1 (Box 32)
    - Seaman and Theatre T[?], Ed Cole luncheon, Richard D. Thompson, Undated; 1 (Box 33)
    - Parts of B.H.S. speaker on timekeeping, lunch at Armstrongs, 1976 October 28 (Box 34)
    - Pat Quinby, Virginia Dean, Undated; 1 (Box 35)
    - Harold Burris-Meyer, Undated; 1 (Box 36)
  - Playbills, negatives (Box 2)
  - Book manuscript (title unknown) (Box 3)
  - Student papers, "diary," address card file (Box 4)
  - American College Theater festival files, writings (Box 5)
  - Converences, consultations, motion pictures, organizations (Box 6)
  - Photographs (framed, unframed) (Box 7)
  - Topical (unsorted), miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Scenery for the Theater manuscript (Box 9)
  - Scenery for the Theater manuscript (Box 10)
  - Photographs, conferences, writings, H. Stein file (Box 11)
  - Scenery for the Theater [correspondence and manuscript] (Box 12)
  - Student papers, drawings, speeches, miscellaneous topical (unsorted) (Box 13)
  - Television [includes course files] (Box 14)
  - Consultant files, alumni files (Box 15)
  - Consultant files, alumni files (Box 16)
  - Teaching, consultant files (Box 17)
  - Teaching, consultant files (Box 18)
  - Topical (unsorted), printed, alumni (Box 19)
  - Drawings, production photographs (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook (Box 21)
- Additional material, 1957-1963; Accession 1990-M-012; 1 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1989 Nov
  Received from: Transferred from the Drama Library, 1989 July 25
  - Joint Council of the Arts in Education, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - National Art Education Association, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - National Council of the Arts in Education (NCAE), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - NCAE, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - NCAE, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - NCAE--program, 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - NCAE--speakers, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - NCAE, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Unsorted papers, 1957-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
- Additional material, Circa 1934-1976; Accession 2007-M-038
  This accession consists of files of the American Educational Theatre Association's architecture project in which Edward Cole participated. The files are arranged by state names within numerically designated geographic regions. The original order of files has been maintained. Regions 11-16 vary between the listing in folder 1 and the actual files.
  - Listing of regions and architectural specifications (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - United States
    - Region 1
      - Northern California (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Nevada (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Region 2
      - Arizona (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Southern California (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Region 3
      - Oregon (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Washington (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Region 4
      - Colorado (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Utah (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Montana (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Region 5
      - Louisiana (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Oklahoma (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Texas (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Texas (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Arkansas (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Region 6
      - Kansas (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Nebraska (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Missouri (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Iowa (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Region 7: Minnesota (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Region 8
      - Illinois (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Wisconsin (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Region 9
      - Ohio (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Michigan (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Indiana (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Region 10
      - Kentucky (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Tennessee (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Alabama (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Georgia (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - North Carolina (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - South Carolina (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Florida (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Virginia (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - West Virginia (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Region 12: New York (Box 3, Folder 36 - 38)
    - Region 13
      - Maryland (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Washington, D.C. (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Region 14
      - East Pennsylvania (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - New Jersey (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Region 15
      - Vermont (Box 4, Folder 43)
      - Maine (Box 4, Folder 44)
      - New Hampshire (Box 4, Folder 45)
      - Rhode Island (Box 4, Folder 46)
      - Connecticut (Box 4, Folder 47 - 49)
      - Massachusetts (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Region 16: Hawaii (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Region 17: Alaska (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Canada, Eastern
    - Region 18
      - Ontario (Box 5, Folder 53)
      - Quebec (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Canada, Western
    - Region 19
      - Manitoba (Box 5, Folder 55)
      - British Colombia (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - International
    - Foreign theaters (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - England (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Germany (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - South Africa (Box 5, Folder 60)